<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-10T23:39:30-08:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">gusev.io</title><subtitle>Peter Gusev's (a.k.a. peetonn) site.&lt;br/&gt;Immersive interactive experiences.&lt;br/&gt;Real-time distributed systems.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">cheLA residence</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/10/21/chela-residence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="cheLA residence" /><published>2018-10-21T03:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-21T03:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/10/21/chela-residence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/2018/10/21/chela-residence.html">&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of March 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.remap.ucla.edu/&quot;&gt;REMAP&lt;/a&gt;, where I currently work, and a number of invited interactive media and visual artists moved down to &lt;a href=&quot;http://chela.org.ar/&quot;&gt;cheLA&lt;/a&gt;, Buenos Aires, for two weeks to organize a &lt;a href=&quot;http://chela.org.ar/archives/2172320&quot;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; for local artists and conduct a series of experiments using &lt;a href=&quot;http://openptrack.org/&quot;&gt;OpenPTrack&lt;/a&gt; motion tracking system, computer vision and machine-learning techniques for a live performance. The theme of the workshop was “interactive spaces with memory”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot was built during these two weeks, which deserves a separate post I’ll write some time later, but I’m glad I had a chance to work back to back with artists, engineers and professionals. It was a valuable experience and I gained knowledge that helped me to understand better my relationship with the emerging world defined by intersection of technology, art and performance.
Due to unforeseen reasons, I couldn’t return back to Los Angeles after the project was over and had to stay few more months in Buenos Aires. Looking back now, I can say that this unexpectedly turned out to be a very productive time for me to submerge deeper into art, meet local and international artists, as well as learn new skills and apply them in practice. cheLA staff were kind enough to allow me to continue my stay in the space and use it’s facilities for my experimentations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;cheLA (/Centro Hipermediático Experimental Latinoamericano/) is a cultural and technological center, located in Parque Patricios, Buenos Aires, Argentina. It started its’ existence in 2003 when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tft.ucla.edu/2011/09/faculty-fabian-wagmister/&quot;&gt;Fabian Wagmister&lt;/a&gt; , UCLA professor and founding director or REMAP, acquired old asbestos factory with the goal of turning it into a place, where artists could work and experiment with modern technology. Today, cheLA offers its’ spaces for artistic residencies, various art&amp;amp;technology workshops and makers studios. It is a huge building, with multiple interconnected warehouse-like spaces, community areas and apartments for residency artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/chela1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cheLA entrance&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/chela2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cheLA&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my team departed, I was left to myself at cheLA for a few weeks before next art residency started. It made sense to use this time to start learning and experimenting with what I always wanted, but couldn’t find time nor place to do it — projection mapping. There are different techniques for projection mapping. The most simple one is based on 2D masking, where you point projector on the object you want to map and mask out areas that should remain black. You do this by drawing 2D shapes around the surfaces of the object, which should receive projected visual content (most likely videos or real-time generated visuals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first experiment, together with &lt;a href=&quot;https://matthewragan.com/&quot;&gt;Matthew&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zoesandoval.com/&quot;&gt;Zoe&lt;/a&gt;, was to project on an weirdly-looking structure — a giant paraboloid on the 2nd floor in cheLA (the structure was an experiment built during one of the architectural workshops held by &lt;a href=&quot;https://tamaco.chela.org.ar/&quot;&gt;TaMaCo&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/mapping.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;TaMaCo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2D mapping is fast and fun technique to use, when you need to quickly projection map something, for example, this airstair at cheLA apartments, where I stayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/stairs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;checLA stairs&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/2d-mapping.png&quot; alt=&quot;2d mapping&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/touchdesigner.png&quot; alt=&quot;touchdesigner projection mapping&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experiments I used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.derivative.ca/&quot;&gt;TouchDesigner&lt;/a&gt; — a node-based programming environment for creative coders, media and visual artists. My previous experience with it was mostly project-scoped and focused on engineering, rather than creative, side of it. Now it was a good time to explore other facets of this powerful system.
TouchDesigner has a small, but very supportive community, where people share their knowledge through tutorials and forum discussions. I’d recommend anyone, who wants to learn TouchDesigner, use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.derivative.ca/Education/ResourcesLearnTeach.asp&quot;&gt;available tutorials&lt;/a&gt; on the official website as a starting point. It is a very interactive system — every change is reflected instantly and visually, so it’s quite easy to grasp basic principles. The more difficult part is to find your own way of expressing your artwork through the system. This is something that is learned through practice.
What’s interesting about studying TouchDesigner — is that any knowledge, learned or discovered, is valuable as it may be applied in unexpected scenarios. This happened to me while I was following one &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.derivative.ca/Events/2015/MUTEK2015WorkshopVideos/&quot;&gt;particular tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on dynamic environment mapping for LED panels using GLSL. While I didn’t have LED panels at my disposal at cheLA, at some point halfway through the tutorial it struck me, that I can adapt the system for making anamorphic projection in a corner between two walls.
The idea behind anamorphic projections is that the projected content makes sense (spatially) only when viewed from a certain point. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NXpSe9xsQYU&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C1ua43UTno4&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; would be good examples of what anamorphic projections are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of anamorphic projection is to make graphical content be recognizable only when viewed from a specific position in space.  Viewed from another angle, the content will be distorted, often times considerably, and won’t make any sense for a viewer. Unlike 2D projection mapping, this type of projection requires additional knowledge about the actual physical space:
	* geometry of the /projection surface/;
	* /projector’s/ physical location relative to the projection surface;
	* /viewpoint’s/ physical location relative to the projection surface.
In my case, the projection surface was a corner between two walls.
There could be two ways of finding projectors’ location relative to the surface. The first one, is to actually measure physical distances between projector and walls and use them to model the scene in 3D. This will take a lot of time and totally depends on the accuracy of the measurements. The second, is to use TouchDesigner’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.derivative.ca/wiki088/index.php?title=CamSchnappr&quot;&gt;3D projection mapping tool&lt;/a&gt;. All I needed to do is to mark /ABCDEF/ points on the actual walls and make sure projection area covered all of the points. Then, you perform mapping between physical /ABCDEF/ surface and a virtual 3D version of it (modeled as two perpendicular rectangles). The process is straightforward and interactive: you select a vertex of your 3D model and then move it’s projected marker onto its’ corresponding point on the physical surface. By the end of this process, a transformation matrix is calculated, representing position of the projector relative to the projection surface, and is applied to the projector’s output. This allows to transform projection media in a way, that it will “lay down” on the physical surface without distortions. Typically, you would assign textures to your projection surface 3D model and you will see them perfectly aligned with the physical structure.
But with anamorphic projection additional work is required. The content must be rendered for a specific, predefined point of view (I chose it arbitrarily - approximately 6ft away from each wall and the floor). This essentially means that your viewer is represented as a camera inside TouchDesigner. The goal is, then, a) to move the viewer-camera in 3D scene according to the viewpoint in physical space and b) render content for this camera using mapping surface as a rendering canvas. The mapping surface essentially serves as a “window” into the virtual 3D environment of your content. I wouldn’t know where to start with implementing this in TouchDesigner, but it turned out that it can be eloquently implemented using GLSL. For those who are interested, there is a sample &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.derivative.ca/Events/2015/MUTEK2015WorkshopVideos/Downloads/OnionSkin_Redux.zip&quot;&gt;GLSL code&lt;/a&gt; that can be adapted for this task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/anamorphic-dia.png&quot; alt=&quot;anamorphic projection diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of interpreting viewer as a camera and mapping surface as a window turned out to be very useful for my next experiment. Just by moving camera you can specify new viewpoint for projection in the physical space. Or, if you turn it the other way around — when your viewer moves in space, you just have to update the location of the camera in 3D scene to maintain illusion of a “window” into the virtual world. Track a person in real-time? I think we have a solution for that…😬
Next several days I was experimenting inside the space, where we set up OpenPTrack system for the workshop in March. After some additional 3D modeling and pulling OpenPTrack data into the system, I was very satisfied with the result. I still need to learn a lot in TouchDesigner to make it look prettier or visually more exciting, but as a prototype and learning exercise, I think it worked out fine =) And I was quite happy I happened to be at cheLA at this time, where I could easily run experiments, trying and combining multiple different techniques and components, from 3D mapping and GLSL, to person tracking and anamorphic projections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/opt-cube.png&quot; alt=&quot;OpenPTrack anamorphic projection using TouchDesigner&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, cheLA offers its’ spaces for regular art residencies, workshops, open studios, various art events, etc., more often than it used to be. We were pleased to contribute to this growth, by building something for cheLA. There is a space called Caldera, with an antique giant boiler, which on its’ own looks quite impressive, serving as a reminder of the huge asbestos factory this building once was.  And in this space, there are colored LED lanterns installed, hanging from the ceiling. These lanterns were programmed some time ago for an interactive installation and were never used again since then. Lanterns are controlled by a power supply box (Phillips Color Kinetics) which reads commands from the network it is connected to. There are a total of 6 lanterns; each lantern has 33 rows of colored LED strips. To set the color, one needs to send a bitmap array 33x6: each column represents one lantern, each pixel in a row represents lantern’s LED row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/linterna_explained.png&quot; alt=&quot;linterna lights&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few days of testing and Touch-coding allowed me to build a graphical interface for controlling lanterns. After the networking part was done in Python (mostly by borrowing code from the installation repo), it was up to my imagination how color pattern for the lanterns might be generated. I implemented four pattern-generation modules: constant, gradient, animated drop and audio equalizer. You can find a demonstration &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/b8DCDB-A2Ok&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; of how it ended up looking.
Interface was implemented in such a way, so that anyone can add modules in plug-and-play fashion — they just need to follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/remap/linterna_touchdesigner#how-to-expand&quot;&gt;pre-defined rules&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/chela-residence/main.png&quot; alt=&quot;linterna lights TouchDesigner UI&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back now, unexpectedly extended stay at cheLA offered me an opportunity, at the right time and the right place. I seen all cycles of cheLA: full of people running projects, visitors attending workshops, art events and parties, art residencies and open studios, emptiness and silence. And it guided me through my own cycles of working, learning, thinking, absorbing community, reflecting back, re-thinking…
I’ll be glad to come back to cheLA one day again, as an artist, collaborator or just a visitor.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="touchdesigner" /><category term="cheLA" /><category term="projection-mapping" /><summary type="html">In the beginning of March 2018 REMAP, where I currently work, and a number of invited interactive media and visual artists moved down to cheLA, Buenos Aires, for two weeks to organize a workshop for local artists and conduct a series of experiments using OpenPTrack motion tracking system, computer vision and machine-learning techniques for a live performance. The theme of the workshop was “interactive spaces with memory”.</summary></entry></feed>